Canada is in the midst of what is so far
the second worst price decline for
inflationadjusted home prices going back
to 1975. The worst decline was in the
1980s with a peakto trough decline of
31%. Today's decline is sitting at 28%
as of December 2025. I updated my
historical Canadian rent versus own
analysis with 2025 data across 12
Canadian cities and the results
challenge the narrative that owning a
home is always a wise financial
decision. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital. If
your identity is tied to owning your
home being a smarter financial decision
than renting, I suggest you stop
watching now.
In 2024, when I last ran this analysis,
hypothetical renters and owners had
built essentially equal wealth over the
prior 20 years. A statistical tie with
an average renter to owner wealth ratio
of 0.99.
But in 2025, real estate prices
continued dropping across most major
Canadian cities, while global stock
markets, where my hypothetical renters
are invested, stayed strong. The result
is that as of December 31st, 2025, the
geometric mean wealth ratio across all
12 cities is now 1.14.
That means that the average hypothetical
renter in my analysis built 14% more
wealth than the hypothetical owner since
January 2005. Before the homeowners
watching this video click away in a
rage, I own my home, too. This isn't a
personal attack on homeowners. But I
want to show you three things in this
video. One is what actually changed in
the Canadian real estate market over the
last few years. Two, the methodology I
use to compare renters to owners using
real historical data. And three, how you
can run these numbers for your specific
situation. Let's start with what has
happened to Canadian real estate.
There's no doubt that prices had gotten
out of hand. This price decline we're
seeing now wasn't a mistake, or at least
it wasn't accidental. Housing
affordability became one of the biggest
issues faced by Canadians in recent
history, and fingers were pointing in
all kinds of different directions.
Monetary policy was making the cost of
borrowing so cheap that people could
afford to pay more for properties. High
levels of immigration were making the
market for our limited housing supply
overly competitive. Foreign investors
were buying up residential properties,
pushing their prices above what
Canadians could afford to pay. and the
proceeds of moneyaundering were flowing
into Canadian real estate. All these
issues were made worse by a lack of
housing supply response to the once
insatiable demand for Canadian housing.
It's worth thinking about some asset
pricing principles for a minute. I'm
sorry guys, I can't help but get into
this nerdy stuff. If we think about
stock prices just just for a second,
I'll come back to real estate. They
represent the discounted expected future
cash flows of a business. When the
market believes a company will do really
well in the future, the higher expected
cash flows will push the stock's price
up. When the market believes the company
is less risky, the lower discount rate
will push the stock price up. It's not
that different with housing. House
prices represent discounted future
rents. When expected future rents are
higher, house prices are higher. When
interest rates are lower, house prices
are higher. Homeowners are buying a real
estate asset that pays them a dividend
equal to the rent they don't have to
pay. Renters pay their housing costs
explicitly by paying rent and can choose
to invest in assets other than real
estate. At the recent peak of Canadian
home prices, some combination of the
issues I mentioned earlier resulted in
Canadian rents, expected future rents,
and home prices becoming some of the
most expensive in the world. It seemed
like prices were never going to stop
going up. I remember while this was
happening, I'd get into online arguments
with people about my baseline assumption
for real estate price appreciation,
which I typically said at 1% above
inflation. People would tell me that is
far too low of an assumption for Canada
specifically and point to the recent
experience of rapidly rising prices as
proof. But markets are adaptive systems.
They respond to their environment
through market forces and policy
changes. Everyone was aware that high
housing prices and rents were a problem
that needed to be addressed. And while
not everyone agreed on the singular
cause, they had a pretty good idea of
the potential causes and the potential
solutions to address each of them.
Accordingly, we have seen rising
mortgage interest rates, especially
relative to the 2021 lows that
correspond with the house price peak.
Canada's immigration system has been
massively overhauled to reduce the
number of immigrants arriving in Canada.
Some areas have introduced foreign
ownership taxes and the federal
government has implemented a temporary
outright ban on foreign purchases of
certain Canadian real estate and the
federal government has launched
initiatives to increase the supply of
affordable housing across Canada. The
effects have been felt across the
country. Rents and prices have fallen a
lot in some cases from their peaks.
Whether this is perceived as good news
or not depends on who you are. I
personally think that increasing housing
affordability is a good thing, but
anyone who had their assets heavily tied
to Canadian real estate, whether as
homeowners, landlords, or investors in
real estate funds is feeling the pain of
what is probably a healthy correction in
real estate prices in many Canadian
cities. Hard lessons are being learned
that real estate is not the magical
low-risk, high return asset that it
appeared to be for many years. Living
through the earlier period of rising
prices and rents made owning a home look
really financially smart and it does
speak to one of the biggest benefits of
owning. By investing in the asset that
you live in, you're protected from being
priced out of your home. This matters if
you want to settle down somewhere
specific. The thing about that
protection though is that it cuts both
ways. When the cost of living in, say,
Toronto increases a lot. Home prices
will tend to increase as well. If you're
a renter in Toronto, rents are going up
and you might need to leave the city. If
you're an owner, while the cost of
Toronto housing is increasing, the value
of your property is also increasing.
You're hedged or protected against the
rising housing costs in your specific
city pricing you out. That has a lot of
value if you really want to stay in one
place. I get it and it's one of the
reasons that I own my home. On the other
hand, when housing costs in Toronto
start to decrease, as they have for the
last few years, property values will
tend to decrease. If you're a long-term
owner with no intention of moving, this
price decrease shouldn't bother you too
much. But if you're affected by the
value of your home, there's no question
that this matters. Renters, on the other
hand, separate their housing costs from
the value of their assets. This can hurt
when housing costs are going up, as they
were previously, and the renters's
investments are not keeping pace. But it
starts to look pretty good when housing
costs and prices are falling and other
assets are not. Because renters are able
to own a diversified portfolio of assets
rather than a single piece of real
estate. I'd say the renter is in a
pretty good situation most of the time,
even though they do have some tail risk
of being priced out of a specific area.
Last year, I made a video and wrote a
paper where I developed a method for
comparing the hypothetical
counterfactual financial outcomes of an
otherwise identical renter and owner in
Canada. I used actual historical data
for home prices, rents, property taxes,
maintenance costs, and a bunch of other
relevant data for 12 Canadian cities
going back to 2005 through to the end of
2024 to answer whether renting or owning
had resulted in more wealth. Think about
it like this. Imagine in January 2005,
you're renting a place to live, paying
the average apartment rent in one of the
12 cities in my sample. You've saved up
enough cash for a 20% down payment and
closing costs based on the average cost
of buying an apartment in whatever city
it is, and you're trying to decide
whether you really want to buy a place
or keep renting and invest that cash in
the stock market. The model then tracks
the counterfactual wealth outcomes
through the net worth of the two
scenarios over time. If you keep
renting, the cash you had saved up for a
potential down payment gets invested in
stocks. And if you buy, the cash goes
towards purchasing the home. Going
forward, the homeowner in the model
always has just enough cash flow
available to cover the costs of owning,
including property taxes, maintenance
costs, and condo fees or strata fees,
insurance, and the mortgage payment if
they have a mortgage. The initial
purchase in the model is financed with
20% down and a 25-year mortgage at the
prevailing mortgage rate at that time.
The renter has the exact same amount of
cash flow available as the owner, but
the renter typically has lower monthly
cash flow costs since they're only
paying rent and a lower amount for
insurance. Rent does increase every year
in the model. That's always a common
question based on the historical rent
increases in each city, which were often
substantial. In the model, the monthly
difference between the owners and
renters's cash flow costs are invested
in the renters's portfolio if they're
positive and withdrawn if they're
negative. Now, I I know everyone always
says the renter might not actually save
the difference. I understand that, but
they could. And some of you, especially
since you're nerding out watching my
personal finance videos, probably would
save the difference. Now, that said, it
is certainly true that if the renter is
not saving that cash flow cost
difference between renting and owning,
they have no chance financially compared
to the owner. The prerequisites for the
renter in the model to build wealth are
saving and investing in the stock
market. If you don't trust yourself to
be a good saver and don't have the
stomach for investing in stocks, owning
a home might make more sense. Though, as
we've seen, you might also need a strong
stomach to own real estate. Sometimes,
there are other good arguments for
owning, like the hedge property that I
mentioned earlier, and tax efficiency if
you've maxed out all of your registered
savings accounts like the RRSP, TFSA,
and FHSA in Canada. It's also true that
strictly from a financial perspective,
either renting or owning might look
better for your specific situation. It
always makes sense to run the numbers
based on the rent you would pay as a
renter and price you would pay as an
owner. In the model, the renters's
portfolio consists of 30% Canadian
stocks and 70% global stocks with an
annual fee of 0.25%
similar to VEQT. This is one of the
places where I think the comparison gets
really interesting. Canadian real estate
in general did not do well for the last
few years, but stock markets around the
world did really well. That can change
in a day, I know, if there's a a market
crash, but looking at what has actually
happened over this period, being
invested in the stock market has been
pretty great. Real estate dropping and
stocks going up made my historical
comparison of renting and owning to the
end of 2024 a lot closer than I would
have guessed when I started the project.
I measured outcomes as the ratio of
renter wealth to owner wealth at the end
of the period and found a geometric mean
average ending wealth ratio of 0.99
across all 12 cities. This means that on
average renters and owners would have
accumulated comparable wealth with a
slight edge for owners in that initial
sample. There was lots of dispersion
with some cities favoring owners and
some favoring renters, but the overall
picture across Canada was surprisingly
even. Since then, real estate has
continued to drop while the stock market
has remained strong and shown off the
benefits of diversification. The US
stock market, for example, slowed down a
bit. It still had a great return, but it
slowed down a bit in 2025, but Canadian
and international stocks did incredibly
well. As of December 31st, 2025, the
geometric mean wealth ratio is 1.14.
This means that on average, hypothetical
renters have now come out ahead of
owners in Canada since January 2005. No
cities flipped, meaning that owners
still come out ahead in the same cities
as before. But the wealth gaps narrowed
pretty dramatically in some places.
Kitchener, Waterlue, and Victoria are
prime examples where as of 2024, owners
had come out way ahead. But as of 2025
year end, the renter to owner wealth
ratio is 0.99 in both of those cities,
suggesting that my hypothetical renters
in those cities only trail owners by a
small margin. These numbers are all
based on historical Canadian data. If
you want to run current numbers for your
specific situation, PWL Capital has a
free online rent versus own calculator
for Canadians. Anyone can use it whether
you're Canadian or not, but it lets you
toggle Canadian taxes on or off for your
investments and the renting scenario.
and it customizes the tax calculations
for your specific province and tax rate.
It's definitely worth checking out if
you're making the rent versus own
decision in Canada today. Sometimes
renting will look better and sometimes
owning will look better on a projection
basis. And importantly, the calculator
only looks at the financial side of the
decision. If you feel good, if you feel
good, numbers aside, about yourself or
about your decision uh to own your home,
this video is not suggesting that you're
wrong. The calculator is not suggesting
that you're wrong. As I mentioned
before, I own my home, too. But I also
don't have a dogmatic view that home
ownership is superior in every possible
way to renting, which is a very common
perception in Canada. The reality is
that owning a home in and of itself is
probably not going to make you happier
or more fulfilled. And renting combined
with discipline, saving, and investing
can be expected to offer comparable
long-term financial outcomes to owning.
Again, I own my home because I live in a
place with very little rental stock. It
would be hard for us to rent if we could
find a rental at all. And I don't want
to have to move. Candidly, that's a nice
thing about owning. There's nothing
wrong with wanting to own your home for
those reasons or whatever reasons you
have. I my my main argument is that
renting is a perfectly reasonable
option. That's all I'm trying to say.
Prior to owning, I rented happily and
successfully for for many years. It was
incredibly useful being a renter, being
able to move at the end of a lease as my
family was growing and my employment was
changing. When we went from in office
work to work from home, I was able to
move very easily. Now, at this point in
my life, I have owned a home for the
same amount of time that I had rented
with a wife and kids. I've been in six
years roughly in each situation. Again,
being with a wife and with an increasing
number of kids, which is now done at at
four. Both were fine. The main
difference being a homeowner makes in my
life is the amount of time and money
that I spend on maintaining and
improving my house, which is a painful
amount. I don't want to talk about it.
My kids still talk about missing some of
our previous rental homes, which were
all nice places. There are nice rentals
out there, but my kids do also like
being settled in in one place. All that
to say, if you're happy renting, don't
let people tell you it's a mistake.
That's a point that should be easier to
make now. That Canadian real estate has
proven that it is in fact a risky asset.
And that on average across 12 major
Canadian cities, a hypothetical renter
could have reasonably built more wealth
than an owner in the stock market from
January 2005 through December 2025.
If you're making the rent versus own
decision right now, run your numbers
with the PWL Capital Calculator. Link is
in the description. It's built
specifically for Canadians and free to
use.